Beyond the myth lies America's greatest betrayal
The Assassination of Jesse James by the Coward Robert Ford is a
drama, western film directed by Andrew Dominik.
Outlaw Jesse James is rumored to be the 'fastest gun in the West'.
An eager recruit into James' notorious gang, Robert Ford eventually grows jealous of the famed outlaw and, when Robert and his
brother sense an opportunity to kill James, their murderous action elevates their target to near mythical status.
Jesse James, played by Brad Pitt.
Robert Ford, played by Casey Affleck.
Charley Ford, played by Sam Rockwell.
Dick Liddil, played by Paul Schneider.
Wood Hite, played by Jeremy Renner.
Ed Miller, played by Garret Dillahunt.
The Assassination of Jesse James by the Coward Robert Ford is a 2007 American epic
revisionist Western film written and directed by Andrew Dominik.
Based on Ron Hansen's 1983 novel of the same name, the film dramatizes the relationship between Jesse
James and Robert Ford, focusing on the events that lead up to the titular killing.
It stars Brad Pitt as James and Casey Affleck as Ford, with Sam Shepard, Mary-Louise Parker, Paul
Schneider, Jeremy Renner, Zooey Deschanel, and Sam Rockwell in supporting roles.
Photography started on August 29, 2005, and ended in December 2005.
Filming took place near Calgary, Canmore, and
Edmonton, Alberta, and Winnipeg, Manitoba.
To achieve the visual style he wanted for the movie, Dominik took influences from many sources, including still
photographers, images clipped from magazines, stills from Days of Heaven, and even Polaroids.
The original edit of the movie was envisioned by Dominik to be "a dark, contemplative
examination of fame and infamy", reaching more than three hours in runtime.
This was opposed by the studio and the film was edited repeatedly.
The Assassination of Jesse James by the Coward Robert Ford had its world premiere at the 64th Venice International Film Festival
on September 2, 2007, and was theatrically released in the United States on September 21, 2007, by Warner Bros.
The film received positive reviews from critics, who particularly praised Pitt and Affleck's performances and
Roger Deakins' cinematography, but was criticized for its long runtime and was a box-office bomb.
At the 80th Academy Awards, it earned two nominations: Best Supporting
Actor for Affleck and Best Cinematography for Deakins.
Affleck was also nominated for a Golden Globe, a Screen Actors Guild Award, and a Critics'
Choice Award for Best Supporting Actor, while Pitt won the Volpi Cup for Best Actor.
It has since gained a large fan following, with many of them organizing
re-releases of the film under the "Jesse James Revival" banner.
The film explores themes of media, killing,
missouri, admiration, hold-up robbery.
The tone is emotional.